Okay, that's recording.
Start the broadcast here.
Okay.
This is my first YouTube video, so I'm pretty excited.
Does someone
want to applaud, you know, you...
Here,
put it up here so people notice.
That's on the video too. Okay, great.
So we're in the משנה mishnah on כ"א ע"ב. kaf aleph amud
bet.
It's like twelve lines from the top. The משנה: mishnah: לא ירבה
לו סוסים אלא כדי מרכבתו וכסף וזהב
לא ירבה לו מאוד אלא כדי ליתן אפסניא.
Lo yarbeh lo susim ella k'dei mirkavto v'chesef v'zahav
lo yarbeh lo me'od ella k'dei litein aspanya. So the king, there's
in addition to not having too many wives, which you learned we
learned about yesterday, he's also not allowed to have too many horses
or too much money.
So the משנה mishnah says that he can't have too many horses
except he's allowed to have enough for like his chariot chariots and
entourage and his cavalry, but and כסף וזהב kesef v'zahav and his
money, he can he's just not allowed to have too much, but
he's allowed to have enough in order to like pay for his
army and pay for the things that he needs.
So I think it's like whatever the need is.
So there's something subjective, but the point is that he can't he
can't just be stocking even if he was stocking in order to
have
in store for later, that might be fine. But if it just
gets to a point where it's just like extraneous wealth or extraneous
horses that are really not serving any function or even any potential
function, then the גמרא's gemara going to go a little deeper into
exactly what what's not permitted. וכותב לו ספר תורה לשמו V'chotev lo
sefer torah lishmo
and he has to write a ספר תורה sefer torah for himself.
יוצא למלחמה מוציאה עמו נכנס
ומכניסה עמו.
Yotzei lamilchama motziah imo
nichnas umachnisah imo. So
and he has to write a ספר תורה sefer torah for himself
and this ספר תורה sefer torah goes with him everywhere. When he
goes out to war, it goes with him, when he comes back
from war, it comes back with him. יושב בדין היתה עמו. Yosheiv
b'din haytah imo. עמו, imo, היתה עמו, haytah imo, כנגד שנאמר והיתה
עמו וקרא
בו כל ימי חייו.
k'neged shene'emar v'haytah imo
v'kara bo kol y'mei chayav. And if he's sitting in judgment, it's
also sitting there right next to him,
because it says that it'll be with him his whole life and
he'll read from it his whole life.
They have like they have these סופרים sofrim who can write really
small and you could have like a really like a pocket size
almost like a pocket-sized תורה. torah. So it presumably seems like it's
something that he can be like that that it could be something
easy to carry around with him. So the
גמרא gemara says: תנו רבנן לא ירבה לו סוסים יכול אפילו כדי
מרכבתו ופרשיו תלמוד לומר לו לו
אינו מרבה אבל מרבה הוא כדי רכבתו ופרשיו.
Tanu rabbanan lo yarbeh lo susim yachol afilu k'dei mirkavto ufarashav talmud
lomar
lo lo eino marbeh aval marbeh hu k'dei rechavto ufarashav. There you
go. So the גמרא gemara says that you can't have too many
horses. So I might have thought that he can't even have too
many horses in his army or his entourage and the תורה torah
says no, תלמוד לומר לו. talmud lomar lo. You can't have too
many horses for himself. For himself he can't have, but he's allowed
to have enough in order for him to like have the appropriate
number of horses in his in his forces. הא מה אני מקיים
סוסים? Ha mah ani mikayeim susim?
So what is סוסים? susim? סוסים בטלנין. Susim batlanin. So what do
we say
when what are we talking about when we're talking about horses? We're
talking about like the empty horses. So if you have
kind of like an entourage, or just like the extraneous horses running
out in front that are just for show. No one's riding them,
no one's doing anything, they're not serving any function, they're not pulling
a chariot, they're just extra horses that are serving no function whatsoever.
So that's going to be the kind of horses that we don't
want him to have too many of. מנין שאפילו סוס אחד והוא
בטל שהוא בלא ירבה? Minayin she'afilu sus echad v'hu batel shehu b'lo
yarbeh? How do I know even one extraneous horse,
one idle horse, is included in לא ירבה? lo yarbeh? תלמוד לומר
למען הרבות סוס. Talmud lomar l'ma'an harbot sus. וכיון דאפילו סוס אחד
והוא בטל קאי בלא ירבה סוסים לא ירבה בסוסים
למה לי? V'keivan d'afilu sus echad v'hu batel kai b'lo yarbeh susim
lo yarbeh
b'susim lamah
li? So they say
okay fine great, the פסוק pasuk says למען הרבות, l'ma'an harbot, למען,
l'ma'an,
oh
the פסוק pasuk למען l'ma'an to include a source, includes a סוס,
sus, a horse. But then once we know that even one horse
is going to be considered בלא ירבה, b'lo yarbeh, why do we
need to say לא ירבה סוסים? lo yarbeh susim? What is the
what's the extra fact that it's plural, what does that do for
you? לעבור בלא תעשה על כל סוס וסוס La'avor b'lo ta'aseh al
kol sus v'sus
to tell you that it's not just like oh once you have
one extra source then all your extra horses become subsumed under that
one איסור issur of just saying like, oh now I'm in the
category of too many horses. No, rather it's saying that each and
every horse that you have that's additional to the ones that you
need, that's going to be considered problematic.
והא דכתב רחמנא לו ve-ha de-chtav rachmana lo and the fact that
the Torah wrote the word לו, lo, לא ירבה לו סוסים, lo
yarbeh lo susim, הלאו הכי ha-lav hachi without it, הוה אמינא hava
amina אפילו כדי רכבו ופרשיו afilu kedei richbo u-farashav נמי לא, nami
lo, לא צריכא לאפושי. lo tzricha le-afushei. So
I would have thought, so you're telling me that had the word
לו lo not been written, I wouldn't have thought that it,
I might have thought, sorry, had the word לו lo not been
written, I might have thought that he wouldn't have been allowed to
even do
for his army itself. And it's saying no, we need it in
order to say that even for that, he shouldn't have too much.
Oh, so sorry. So that לו lo in order to teach us
that
don't think that there should ever be a situation where you limit
what you actually need for the kingship.
Great. וכסף וזהב לא ירבה לו אלא כדי ליתן אספניא.
ve-chesef ve-zahav lo
yarbeh lo
ela kedei liten aspanya.
תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, וכסף וזהב לא ירבה לו ve-chesef ve-zahav lo
yarbeh lo יכול אפילו
כדי ליתן אספניא,
yachol afilu kedei liten
aspanya, תלמוד לומר לו.
talmud lomar lo. לו lo אינו מרבה אבל מרבה הוא כדי ליתן
אספניא.
lo eino marbeh aval
marbeh hu kedei liten aspanya.
So same thing we said with the horses, the word לו lo
is teaching you that it can't be extraneous for personal reasons, but
for the army
and for the functioning of the crown, it's permitted. והא דכתב רחמנא
לו, ve-ha de-chtav rachmana lo, הלאו הכי ha-lav hachi הוה אמינא hava
amina אפילו כדי ליתן אספניא נמי
לא.
afilu kedei liten aspanya
nami lo. So what, you're saying the Torah had to say לו
lo to that? I would have, do you really, I really would
have thought that had the פסוק pasuk not said לו, lo, that
not that the personal is אסור, assur, that he wouldn't be allowed
to have enough money to pay for his army? Like who would
ever think that? Of course you'd be able to do that. So
לא צריכא להרחבה. lo tzricha le-harchavah.
No, so we need it in order
to let him know that he really shouldn't, it's really just about
personal things, that for the army he can even have an expanded,
an expanded amount of money. He really should make sure that he
takes care of that. And the לו lo is saying that it's
extremely limited to just personal reasons. השתא דאמרת לו לדרשה. hashta de-amrat
lo le-drasha.
Now that we have לו lo for a דרשה. drasha. לא ירבה
לו נשים, lo yarbeh lo nashim, מאי דרשת ביה mai darsht bei
למיעוט הדיוטות? lemiut hedyotot? So we need it for a דרשה, drasha,
we're going to compare it to לא ירבה לו נשים. lo yarbeh
lo nashim. So what do we learn from that? To exclude, to
exclude it from הדיוטות. hedyotot. So the גמרא gemara is saying that
for לא ירבה לו נשים, lo yarbeh lo nashim,
the לו lo comes to teach you that even though a regular
person is allowed to have lots of as many wives as he
wants, a king has to be limited in his wives. רבי יהודה
רמי. Rabbi Yehuda rami.
כתיב ketiv ויהי לשלמה ארבעים אלף אורוות סוסים למרכבתו,
vayehi lishlomo arbaim
elef urvot susim le-mirkavto, וכתיב u-chetiv ויהי לשלמה ארבעה אלפים אורוות סוסים.
vayehi lishlomo arba'at alafim urvot susim. הא כיצד? ha keitzad? אם ארבעים
אלף אצטבלאות היו, im arbaim elef itztablaot hayu, כל אחד ואחד היו
בו ארבעה אלפים אורוות סוסים. kol echad ve-echad hayu vo arba'at alafim
urvot susim. ואם ארבעה אלפים אצטבלאות היו, ve-im arba'at alafim itztablaot hayu,
כל אחד ואחד היו בו ארבעים אלף אורוות סוסים.
kol echad ve-echad hayu
vo arbaim elef urvot susim. So Rabbi Yehuda points out that there
seems to be two conflicting פסוקים. psukim. One פסוק pasuk seems to
be saying that Shlomo Hamelech had 40,000 stables for his cavalry
or for all his horses, and then the other פסוק pasuk seems
to say it's ארבעה אלפים, arba'at alafim, that's 4,000 stables for his
horses. So then we say that either there was 4,000 houses with
40,000 individual stable units in each, or 40,000 with 4,000 in each.
So either way you're going to wind up with
160 million? 1.6?
16 million, is that the right number there? Seven zeros? Yeah, I
don't know.
רבי יצחק רמי כתיב אין כסף נחשב אין כסף נחשב
בימי שלמה למאומה כתיב ויתן שלמה את הכסף בירושלים כאבנים.
Rabbi Yitzchak rami ksiv
ein kessef nechshav ein kessef nechshav bimei Shlomo le'me'umah ksiv vayiten Shlomo
et hakessef b'Yerushalayim ka'avanim.
So רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak says, oh, I'm going to point out
another conflict. In one פסוק pasuk it seems like אין כסף נחשב
בימי שלמה למאומה, ein kessef nechshav bimei Shlomo le'me'umah, they didn't have
too much money. And in another פסוק pasuk it says money was,
they had so much money in Jerusalem, it was like stones. So
either it's saying that there was so much, or like אבנים avanim
that they were imported, the money was like an imported thing that
was going on in Jerusalem at the time. לא קשיא כאן קודם
שנשא שלמה את בת פרעה כאן לאחר שנשא שלמה את בת פרעה.
lo kashya kan kodem shenasa Shlomo et bat Paroh kan le'achar shenasa
Shlomo et bat Paroh. Pre-marriage money was not in overabundance, but post-marriage
it became an important significant thing in the kingdom.
It wasn't אין כסף נחשב בימי שלמה למאומה, ein kessef nechshav bimei
Shlomo le'me'umah, there was so much it wasn't worth anything.
Oh, is that?
I think so. Yeah,
yeah.
There's also another note that says he can't accumulate all this through
taxes, but if it's given as gifts, then it's alright.
So that's one reason
why post-בת פרעה, bat Paroh, that was like a dowry,
that was like...
But that was early on, so I don't know if it's just
related to פרעה, Paroh, but just in general the concept of he
can't do it by
tax.
Oh, so I mean just okay,
so he's saying that the first one is there was so much
money that was like a supply and demand thing,
and then the ones that they married בת פרעה bat Paroh and
then they became,
they had less money?
Because they got richer after he married בת פרעה. bat Paroh.
Yeah, that's confusing. The first one sort of sounds like an issue
that they printed too much money and then, right? Okay. אמר רבי
יצחק בשעה שנשא שלמה את בת פרעה ירד גבריאל, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak
besha'ah shenasa Shlomo et bat Paroh yarad Gavriel, so when שלמה Shlomo
married the daughter of פרעה, Paroh, גבריאל Gavriel came down ונעץ קנה
בים ועלה שרטון ועליו נבנה כרך גדול שברומי. venatz kanah bayam ve'alah
sirtun ve'alav nivneh krach gadol shebi'Romi. Okay,
this is like a, as opposed to Romulus and Remus, this is
a different founding story for the city of Rome, that somehow שלמה
Shlomo and בת פרעה's bat Paroh marriage,
at that moment גבריאל Gavriel came down and put sort of the
foundation reed of Rome.
As a punishment, I guess, huh? Do you think? In other words,
your enemy, it's the beginning of Rome
which
is going to be the enemy of...
Right, I'm guessing as a punishment?
Sounds good to me, I wasn't sure exactly how to interpret it.
I was trying to come up with other creative explanations.
Usually they say to Israel's great enemy, right, okay.
ואמר רבי יצחק מפני מה לא נתגלו טעמי תורה.
ve'amar
Rabbi Yitzchak
mipnei mah lo nitgalu ta'amei Torah.
So how come in general we don't know the reasons for things,
for מצוות mitzvot in
the תורה? Torah? שהרי שתי מקראות נתגלו טעמן נכשל בהם גדול העולם.
she'harei shtei mikra'ot nitgalu ta'aman nichshal bahem gadol ha'olam. Because the two
פסוקים psukim where he's given the reasons,
don't have too many horses, don't have too many wives,
have reasons,
and once you give a reason then a person is going to
think that the reason is not going to apply to them. So
כתיב לא ירבה לו נשים, ksiv lo yarbeh lo nashim, אמר שלמה
אני ארבה ולא אסור, Amar Shlomo ani arbeh velo asur, וכתיב ויהי
לעת זקנת שלמה נשיו הטו את לבבו. ucheshiv vayehi le'et ziknat Shlomo
nashav hitu et levavo.
So שלמה Shlomo said, ah, well, I'm the smartest guy in the
world, it's going to be fine for me. Now when he got
older, then they started messing with him. כתיב לא ירבה לו סוסים,
ksiv lo yarbeh lo susim, אמר שלמה אני ארבה ולא אשיב. Amar
Shlomo ani arbeh velo ashiv. So שלמה's Shlomo like, no, no, I'm
an exception to this rule. וכתיב ותצא מרכבה ממצרים שש, ucheshiv vatetze
merkavah mi'Mitzrayim shesh, and then he winds up falling into the same
exact trap which the תורה Torah didn't want us to do.
Just to connect it back a couple days ago, there was a
מחלוקת machlokes and איכא בינייהו ika beinayhu and one, one Rabbi was
דורש טעמא דמצוות doresh ta'ama de'mitzvot and one is not. So it's
just interesting that
the תורה Torah doesn't give us reasons, but there are there are
Rabbis in חז"ל Chazal who do like explain the reasons later on.
Totally, and then I think the interesting phenomenon is that like once
there are reasons, then you have lots of people running around going
like, oh, that doesn't, ah, this doesn't apply, this shouldn't apply to
me.
You make a חקירה chakira and then you give reasons and then
you say, well, I'm on this side of the חקירה chakira and
therefore it's permitted, right?
Exactly. But not even that, you could say like, oh, I agree
that was the reason, now that reason shouldn't apply
anymore, so
I'm fine.
I know, but this is from a מדרש Midrash that says פרעה's
Paroh daughter brought musical instruments that were used in idol worship and
she introduced the practice of idol worship in Israel, and a practice
that God ultimately punished with the Roman destruction of the Temple.
So all the seeds were planted in...
I mean, it was idol worship before.
There was always idol worship, yeah. Except for like 40 years.
Right, but the point being that, which is whatever on the longer
symbolic, all that conversation, that שלמה Shlomo is the one that builds
the Temple, but along with building the Temple, there were the seeds
for...
Very good, very good. Yes, he also was causing its destruction. Okay,
good.
דכותב
ספר תורה Torah לשמו *Dekotev sefer torah lishmo*.
תנו רבנן *Tanu rabanan*: שלא יתנאה בשל אבותיו *shelo yitna'eh beshel avotav*.
We have a משנה Mishna. *Mishnah* that says that he shouldn't use
the one that he inherits. So אף על פי שהניח לו אבותיו
לאדם ספר תורה Torah, מצווה לכתוב משלו *Af al pi she-hiniach lo
avotav le-adam sefer torah mitzvah lichtov mishelo*. Even if you inherit a
ספר תורה Torah *Sefer Torah*, you still have a מצווה *mitzvah* to
write one for yourself. שנאמר Shene'emar, ועתה כתבו לכם את השירה *Shene'emar:
Ve'ata kitvu lachem et hashirah*. איתיבי *Eitivi*, so we have a ברייתא
braita. *Baraita* that seems to challenge this. וכותב לו ספר תורה Torah,
לשמו שלא יתנאה בשל אחרים *Vechotev lo sefer torah lishmo shelo yitna'eh
beshel acherim*. What we said that he has to write one for
himself, it's not about excluding the one that he inherits, rather one
that was written for someone else. מלך melech אין הדיוט לא *Melech
in, hedyot lo*.
So for a מלך *king*, we say yes, that's the case; for
a הדיוט *hedyot*, no.
A הדיוט *hedyot* could just use somebody else's. לא צריכה לשתי תורות
Torot *Lo tzericha lishtei torot*. So no, we need both of these
teachings for the two תורות *Torahs*. דתניא D'tanya, וכתב לו את משנה
וגומר *Detanya: Vechatav lo et mishneh vegomer*. כותב לשמו שתי תורות *Chotev
lishmo shtei torot*. אחת שיוצאה ונכנסת עמו ואחת שמונחת לו בבית גנזיו
*Achat sheyotza venichneset imo ve'achat shemunachat lo be-veit genazav*.
So he says he actually doesn't just have one תורה Torah *Torah*,
he actually has two תורות *Torahs*. One תורה Torah *Torah* goes in
and out with him to war, sort of his travel תורה Torah
*Torah*, and then he has another תורה Torah *Torah* that he keeps
in his storehouse. אותה שיוצאה ונכנסת עמו *Otah sheyotza venichneset imo*.
So let's read the differences, it's just kind of interesting. עושה אותה
כמין קמיע ותולה בזרועו שנאמר שויתי ה' לנגדי תמיד כי מימיני בל
אמוט *Oseh otah kemin kamei'a vetoleh bizro'o shene'emar Shiviti Hashem lenegdi tamid
ki mimini bal emmot*. So they would actually have it placed in
some sort of receptacle or vessel that would then be attached to
him that he'd be able to walk around with. Sort of feels
a little like תפילין *Tefillin*-esque or that he's wearing some sort of
like satchel. ואינו נכנס בה לא לבית המרחץ ולא לבית הכסא *Ve'eino
nichnas bah lo le-veit hamerchatz velo le-veit hakisei*. But just so you
know, the one that travels with him everywhere doesn't go everywhere everywhere,
like it doesn't go into the bathroom, it doesn't go into the
spa house or the bathhouse.
I just thought I like... I love the... I feel like this
is a great דרש *drash* to use it at some point in
some context,
the idea of like everybody having two תורות *Torahs*. There's like the
inner תורה Torah *Torah* or the תורה *Torah* that you keep in
your גניזה *genizah* and the תורה *Torah* that you walk around with.
You go like deeper... lots of different ways to apply that or
make דרש *drash* on it, but I think it's a powerful idea.
Whether you're the same on the inside and the outside...
so not just the same on the inside and... right.
So yeah, what's your תורה *Torah* to the world versus what you're
really doing it...
so I think the inside-outside, but also like the idea that it's
not crazy for there to be different modes. There's a mode... there's
a תורה *Torah* that you utilize when you're out and about in
the world and there's a different kind of תורה *Torah* that you
use when you're home. The תורה *Torah* can mean different things in
different places.
והיתה עמו וקרא בו *Ve-hayeta imo ve-kara bo*. He has it with
him and he is to read from it. מקום הראוי לקרוא בו
*Makom hara'ui likro bo*. So that's going to limit it to a
place where it's appropriate to read from it. אמר מר זוטרא ואיתימא
מר עוקבא בתחילה ניתנה תורה לישראל בכתב עברי ולשון הקודש *Amar Mar
Zutra ve'iteima Mar Ukva: Batchila nitna torah le-Yisrael bichtav Ivri u-leshon hakodesh*.
חזרה וניתנה להם בימי עזרא Ezra בכתב אשורית Ashurit? ולשון ארמית *Chazra
venitna lahem bimei Ezra bichtav Ashurit u-leshon Aramit*. Okay, so now we
get into the question of what language was the תורה *Torah* written
in? So מר עוקבא *Mar Ukva* says that initially the תורה *Torah*
was given in כתב ktav עברי *Ktav Ivri* and לשון הקודש *Leshon
Hakodesh*. So are you familiar with the difference between כתב ktav עברי
*Ktav Ivri* and כתב אשורית Ashurit? *Ktav Ashurit*? So
כתב *Ktav*... what? They're like different languages basically. כתב אשורית *Ktav Ashurit*
is the letters that you're familiar with, that's like the letters that
are in your גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*. כתב עברי *Ktav Ivri*, if you
look at a מאירי *Me'iri*'s גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*...
so the letters are a little different, if you like...
they're a lot like softer, I would say, in their features, and
they look a little bit... some of the letters actually look a
little different.
It looks like
Ivri is less developed, I'd
say.
Okay.
כתב עברי *Ktav Ivri*...
okay. ולשון הקודש *U-leshon
Hakodesh*. So originally written in עברי *Ivri* and לשון הקודש *Leshon Hakodesh*,
then in the time of עזרא Ezra. *Ezra* it's actually written in
Aramaic
with כתב
אשורית *Ktav Ashurit*, which is our letters. ביררו להן לישראל כתב אשורית
ולשון הקודש והניחו להדיוטות כתב עברי
ולשון ארמי *Bereru lahen
le-Yisrael ktav Ashurit u-leshon hakodesh vehinihu la-hedyotot ktav Ivri u-leshon Arami*. So
we say but
then eventually when בני ישראל Yisrael *Bnei Yisrael* leave Israel, then we
have the כתב אשורית *Ktav Ashurit* with לשון הקודש *Leshon Hakodesh*, which
is what we have now. And for the הדיוטות *hedyotot* they used
to leave it in Aramaic with כתב עברי *Ktav Ivri*. מאן הדיוטות
*Man hedyotot*? Who are the הדיוטות *hedyotot*? אמר רב חסדא כותאי *Amar
Rav Chisda: Kuta'ei*. The כותים *Cutim*. מאי כתב עברי *Mai ktav Ivri*?
So what is כתב עברי *Ktav Ivri*? אמר רב חסדא כתב ליבונה
*Amar Rav Chisda: Ktav libona*. So רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* says it's
the כתב *Ktav* of ליבונה *Libona*, which he... it's a certain place,
it's unclear what it actually means. תניא Tanya רבי Rabbi יוסי אומר
omer ראוי היה עזרא Ezra שתינתן תורה על ידו לישראל אילמלא לא
*Tanya: Rabbi Yosei omer: Raui haya
Ezra she-tinaten torah al yado le-Yisrael ilmalei lo*. So עזרא actually was
like great enough that he could have merited bringing the תורה to
the Jewish people, but the only reason he didn't was because משה
Moshe had done it first.
And now we're going to go through a bunch of examples of
interesting textual parallels between
משה Moshe and ספר עזרא. Sefer Ezra. So starting with משה Moshe
who אומר משה
עלה אל האלהים
Moshe alah el
ha-Elohim ועזרא ve-Ezra הוא אומר hu omer הוא עזרא עלה מבבל. hu
Ezra oleh mi-Bavel. מה עליה האמור כאן תורה אף עליה האמור לה.
Ma aliyah ha-amur kan Torah af aliyah
ha-amur ha-lah Torah. So they have the word עולה oleh in both
cases and one is when משה Moshe goes up to get the
תורה, the other one is when he goes up from בבל. Bavel.
You can make like an argument that this is less about תורה
more about like a
Zionism here we're paralleling the going up to ישראל
with going to receive the תורה, which is something like a one
interesting idea there. ומשה אומר
ואותי צוה ה' בעת ההיא ללמד
אתכם חוקים ומשפטים.
U-Moshe omer ve-oti tzivah Hashem ba-eit ha-hi le-lamed
etchem
chukim u-mishpatim. ועזרא אומר כי עזרא הכין לבבו לדרוש את תורת ה'
ולעשות וללמד בישראל חוק ומשפט. Ve-Ezra omer ki Ezra heichin levavo lidrosh
et Torat Hashem ve-la'asot u-le-lamed be-Yisrael chok u-mishpat. So we see a
similar language of ללמד חוקים ומשפטים, le-lamed chukim u-mishpatim, ללמד חוק ומשפט.
le-lamed chok u-mishpat. ואף על פי שלא נתנה תורה על ידו נשתנה
על ידו הכתב. Ve-af al pi she-lo nitenah Torah al yado nishtanah
al yado ha-ktav. So even though the תורה wasn't written by his
hand, it did change on his hand. What?
Yeah. שינה על ידו הכתב Shinah al yado ha-ktav שנאמר וכתב
הנשתון כתוב ארמית ומתורגם ארמית.
she-ne'emar ve-ktav ha-nishtevan katuv Aramit u-meturgam
Aramit. וכתיב לא כהלין כתבא למיקרא ופשרא להודעא למלכא.
Ve-chtiv lo kahalin ktava
le-mikra u-pishra le-hoda'ah le-malka. וכתיב וכתב את משנה התורה הזאת כתב הראוי
להשתנות. Ve-chtiv ve-ktav et mishneh ha-Torah ha-zot ktav ha-ra'uy le-hishtanot.
So we have these פסוקים psukim from עזרא and דניאל Daniel that
imply that it was that it was changed and from דברים Devarim
where we דרשן darshen כתב את משנה התורה הזאת ktav et mishneh
ha-Torah ha-zot that you could write it in a way that it's
a כתב that could be changed or could be altered later. למה
נקרא אשורית? Lamma nikra Ashurit? So why, what is the source of
the word אשורית? שעלה עמהם מאשור She-alah imahem me-Ashur because these letters
came from
אשור. Ashur. תניא we have a ברייתא. braita. רבי אומר בתחלה כתב
זה נתנה תורה לישראל כיון שחטאו נהפך להם לרועץ כיון שחזרו בהן
החזירו להם שנאמר שובו לביצרון אסירי התקוה
גם היום מגיד משנה אשיב לך.
Rebbe omer bi-tchilah ktav zeh nitenah Torah le-Yisrael keivan she-chat'u nehepach lahem
le-ra'atz keivan she-chazru ba-hem hecheziru lahem she-ne'emar shuvu le-vitzaron
asirei ha-tikvah gam hayom magid mishneh ashiv lach.
So he says oh don't think that all these changes, these changes
aren't later changes that happened in the time of עזרא. In fact
even this is a model that we saw even in the beginning
when the תורה was first given. The תורה was given in one
kind of language, then they sinned and the words got a different
language, and then when they do תשובה teshuvah it comes back to
the original language, which I think is a way of
in my opinion would be sort of like feeling theologically problematic with
what עזרא does, but if you feel like that these are these
initial different kinds of modes, these different scripts were already back at
הר סיני, Har Sinai, then you could feel much more comfortable with
the idea of the תורה being written
in different languages or different scripts or fonts. למה
נקרא שמה אשורית? Lamma nikra shmah Ashurit? So what's, why is it
called אשורית? שמאושרת בכתב She-me'usheret bi-chtav because it's a very rich language,
a very rich text. רשב"א, Rashba, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר משום
רבי אלעזר בן פרטא שאמר משום רבי אלעזר המודעי כתב זה לא
נשתנה כל עיקר.
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer mishum Rabbi Elazar ben Perata she-amar mishum
Rabbi Elazar
ha-Moda'i ktav zeh lo nishtanah kol ikar. He says no actually the
כתב never changed שנאמר ווי העמודים. she-ne'emar vavei ha-amudim. So because we
have the פסוק pasuk of ווי העמודים. vavei ha-amudim. מה עמודים לא
נשתנו אף ווים לא נשתנו. Ma amudim lo nishtanu af vavim lo
nishtanu. And רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon talked about this like a few
months ago in one of his things of the idea that each,
there's a וו vav at the top right of each column starts
with a וו vav except for the first one I guess.
No there's five or six.
There's five or six. And he says just like the columns always
stay the same so too the וו vav is never changed. The
וו vav like the way the וו vav is written never changed.
The issue is just that we have a lot of
different column breakdowns in different תורות and things did get altered. So
it's okay. So ואומר ואל היהודים ככתבם וכלשונם. ve-omer ve-el ha-Yehudim ki-chtavam
ve-khilshonam. מה לשונם לא שנה אף כתבם לא נשתנה.
Ma leshonam lo shanah
af ktavam lo nishtanah.
And we also have a פסוק pasuk in אסתר Esther which says
ככתבם וכלשונם ki-chtavam ve-khilshonam and he's like oh just like their language
didn't change so too their writing didn't change. ומאני מקיים את משנה
התורה הזאת? U-mani mekayem et mishneh ha-Torah ha-zot? לשתי תורות אחת שיוצאה
ונכנסת עמו ואחת שמונחת לו בבית גנזיו. Li-shtei Torot achat she-yotzah ve-nichnesah
imo ve-achat she-munachat lo be-veit ginzav. או שיוצאה ונכנסת עמו עשאן כמין
קמיע ותולה בזרועו שנאמר שויתי ה' לנגדי תמיד. O- she-yotzah ve-nichnesah imo
osatan kemin kame'a ve-toleh bi-zro'o she-ne'emar shiviti Hashem le-negdi tamid. ואידך האי
שויתי מאי דריש ביה? Ve-idach hai shiviti mai darish beih?
So the other opinion and this is referring to
The person who thinks that, one second, the
person who thinks that if
you don't think that he carries it around with him all the
time, so what does שיוויתי ה' לנגדי תמיד Shivisi Hashem lenegdi tamid
teach you? So מאי דריש ביה? mai darish bei? ההוא מיבעי ליה,
hahu mibayei lei, so
he needs this drasha, he needs this pasuk for a different
drasha, כי
הא דאמר רב חנא
בר ביזנא דאמר רב חנא בר ביזנא ki
ha d'amar Rav Chana
bar Bizna d'amar Rav Chana bar Bizna אמר רבי שמעון חסידא amar
Rabbi Shimon Chasida המתפלל צריך שיראה עצמו כאילו שכינה כנגדו
hamispallel tzarich sheyireh atzmo ke'ilu
Shechina kenegdo שנאמר שיוויתי ה' לנגדי תמיד. shenemar Shivisi Hashem lenegdi tamid.
So שיוויתי ה' לנגדי תמיד Shivisi Hashem lenegdi tamid either means that
how the מלך is supposed to carry around the תורה or it
means about how we're supposed to approach תפילה tefillah that we're always
supposed to think of the שכינה Shechina being in front of or
opposite you. ולרבי שמעון דאמר כתב זה לא נשתנה, ulerabbi Shimon d'amar
kesav zeh lo nishtanah, so for Rabbi Shimon who says the writing
never changed, מאי לא כהלין כתבא למקרא? mai lo kahalin kesava lemakra?
So what does he do with the פסוק pasuk of לא כהלין
כתבא למקרא lo kahalin kesava lemakra that we have this פסוק pasuk
in דניאל Daniel that seems like that the implies that there's language
or words that are different than other language and words? So how
does he interpret that? אמר רב בגמטריא. Amar Rav: begimatraya. And I
tried preparing this for a long time and I don't understand this
next part, so I'll read through it in the גמרא, Gemara explain
what I understood, and then we can come back to it later.
יתט יתט אדך פוגחמט. itat itat adach pugachmat. למאי פרשיהו? מנא מנא
תקל ופרסין. lemai parshiyahu? Mene mene tekel upharsin. So it seems like
that the in ספר דניאל Sefer Daniel when there was writing on
the wall, is that where that expression comes from?
From בלשאצר? Belshazzar?
Yeah, from בלשאצר. Belshazzar. So the words were written like in a
really strange language and it was like a letter reversal game, a
sort of like a cryptogram. So when we say לא כהלין כתבא
lo kahalin kesava that the words were the letters were shifted around.
I think they said that this maybe, I know I just said
I wasn't going to try to explain it, but I'm going to
try to explain what I understand.
That there's like a letter reversal system where an אלף Aleph is
represented by ת Taf and a ב Bet is represented by ש
Shin and a ג Gimel is represented by ר Reish and a
ד Dalet is represented by ק. Kuf. So the letters are going
to seem like gibberish, but if you replace it with its opposite
letter on the earlier the other half of the alphabet,
then
it will make
sense. תקיל תקילתא במאזניא והשכחת חסיר. פרס: פריסת מלכותך ויהיבת למדי ופרס.
ושמואל אמר: ממתוס ננקפי אאלרן. רבי יוחנן אמר: אנם אנם לקנ וסרפו.
רב אשי אמר: נמא נמא קתל פורסין Tekil: tekilta bemaznaya vehishkachat chasir.
Peras: perisat malchusach vehivvas lemadi uperas. Ushmuel amar: Memtous nenkapi aalran. Rabbi
Yochanan amar: Anam anam lakan visarfu. Rav Ashi amar: Nama nama katal
porsin.
So I guess they all have different sort of interpretations of what
the writing on the wall means using different models or modes of
interpreting this code.
And I can't tell you exactly what each of them is trying
to say the words should mean. משנה. Okay, we have 25 minutes
now to get through another עמוד amud and a half. אין רוכבין
על סוסו ואין יושבין על כסאו ואין משתמשין בשרביטו ואין רואין אותו
כשהוא מסתפר ולא כשהוא ערום ולא כשהוא בבית המרחץ שנאמר שום תשים
עליך מלך שתהא אימתו עליך. Ein rochvin al suso ve'ein yoshvin al
kiso ve'ein mishtamshin beshravito ve'ein ro'in oso keshehu mistaper velo keshehu arum
velo keshehu beveit hamerchatz shenemar som tasim alecha melech shetehe eimaso alecha.
So the king, you're not allowed to ride on his horse, you
can't sit on his chair, you can't use his scepter,
and you cannot see him when he's getting his haircut, or while
he's naked, or in the bathhouse because it says שום תשים עליך,
som tasim alecha, it should be on you a king, his אימה
eimah should be עליך, alecha, you should there should be a level
of fear or awe towards him, and all these things are going
to lower his stature and status in your eyes.
אמר רב יעקב אמר רבי יוחנן אבישג מותרת לשלמה ואסורה לאדוניה מותרת
לשלמה דמלך היה ומלך משתמש בשרביטו של מלך ואסורה לאדוניה דהדיוט הוא.
Amar Rav Yaakov amar Rabbi Yochanan: Avishag mutteres liShlomo va'asura le'Adoniyah. Mutteres
liShlomo demalech hayah umelech mishtamesh beshravito shel melech va'asura le'Adoniyah dehediot hu.
So
אבישג, Avishag, what, what does who's אבישג? Avishag?
Yeah, אבישג השונמית Avishag HaShunamit was a woman
who in ספר שמואל Sefer Shmuel who comes to take care of
דוד David at the end of his life.
And the point is that אדוניה Adoniyah we say
it's אסור assur for him to sleep with her, but שלמה Shlomo
was allowed to because שלמה Shlomo himself became a king and a
king is allowed to use something that a king used for lack
of better terminology, sorry. מאי היא דכתיב והמלך דוד זקן בא בימים
ויאמרו לו עבדיו יבקשו וכתיב ויבקשו נערה יפה וכתיב והנערה יפה עד
מאד ותהי למלך סוכנת ותשרתהו. Mai hi dechsiv Vehamalech David zaken ba
bayamim veyomru lo avadav yevakshu uchsiv vayivakshu na'arah yafah uchsiv vehan'arah yafah
ad me'od vesehi lamelech sochenet vesisharsehu.
So we're explaining who אבישג Avishag is and these are all the
פסוקים pesukim from מלכים Melachim that explain her role in the kingdom
or with דוד. David. אמרה נינסבין. Amrah ninsavin. So she said to
him, marry me. אמר לה. Amar lah. She says this to אבישג
Avishag and דוד David originally. So דוד David is an old... So
דוד David is an older man, this young woman comes to sort
of be his caretaker, companion, keep him warm, and she says marry
me and he says no it's אסור assur for me to marry
you. אמר לה חסרא דגנב ואנפשיה לשלמא נקיט. Amar lah chasra d'ganav
v'anafshaih l'shlama nakit.
So she says like it's not you're saying it's אסור assur for
you, you're just, you're just old and weak and not strong enough
and you're afraid that you're not going to be able to have
sex with me. So this is sort of her accusation. Like don't
try to hide behind הלכה halacha here. Like I know that you're
really hiding behind your own insecurities or inabilities around your manhood. So
אמר להו amar lehu for lack of a better term, sorry, אמר
להו amar lehu קראו לי לבת שבע. karu li l'Batsheva. So he
says don't accuse me of that. He says someone someone bring בת
שבע Batsheva over here. So he calls בת שבע. Batsheva. כתיב ותבא
בת שבע אל המלך החדרה. Ketiv vatavo Batsheva el hamelech hachedra. אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב באותה שעה קינחה בת שבע בשלוש עשרה מפות.
Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav b'ota sha'ah
kincha Batsheva b'shlosh esrei mapot.
So this is the I'm not sure exactly what the sexual implication
here is, but that look at what רש״י Rashi says.
Okay so רש״י Rashi
says, maybe I was sure and didn't want to say it. No.
קינחה בת שבע שלוש עשרה ביאות ומקנחין בין תשמיש לתשמיש ובמקרא זה
כתובין שלוש עשרה תיבות ותבא בת שבע אל המלך החדרה והמלך זקן
מאד ואבישג השונמית משרתת את המלך. Kincha Batsheva shlosh esrei be'ot u'mekanchin
bein tashmish l'tashmish u'v'mikra zeh ketuvin shlosh esrei teivot vatavo Batsheva el
hamelech hachedra v'hamelech zaken me'od v'Avishag haShunamit msharetet et hamelech.
Yeah, the idea being that they had sex thirteen times and she
was cleaning herself between each time. So he says, don't, don't challenge
my virility or my ability to have sex like and he showed
off, I guess, with בת שבע. Batsheva. אמר רב שמן בר אבא
בא וראה כמה קשים גירושין שהרי דוד המלך התירו לו ליחד ולא
התירו לו לגרש. Amar Rav Shemen bar Abba bo u're'eh kamah kashin
gerushin sheharei David HaMelech hitiro lo l'yached v'lo hitiro lo l'garesh. So
he says, here we're seeing how how hard it is to divorce
to divorce somebody to the extent that דוד David who could have
easily have divorced one of his first eighteen wives in order to
marry אבישג, Abishag, we quicker permitted him to have יחוד
yichud with the woman who he wouldn't be able to sleep with
rather than than התירו לו לגרש hitiro lo l'garesh than permit the
divorce. אמר אלעזר כל המגרש את אשתו ראשונה אפילו מזבח מוריד עליו
דמעות. Amar Elazar kol hamgaresh et ishto rishonah afilu mizbe'ach morid alav
dmaot. Anybody who divorces his first wife even the מזבח mizbe'ach cries
for him. שנאמר וזאת שנית תעשו כסות דמעה את מזבח ה' בבכי
ובאנקה מאין עוד פנות אל המנחה ולקחת רצון מידכם. Shene'emar v'zot shenit
ta'asu kesot dimah et mizbe'ach Hashem b'vechi u'v'anaka me'ein od pnot el
hamincha v'lakachat ratzon miyedchem. וכתיב ואמרתם על מה על כי ה' העיד
בינך ובין אשת נעוריך אשר אתה בגדתה בה והיא חברתך ואשת בריתך.
U'chetiv va'amartem al mah al ki Hashem he'id beinecha u'vein eshet ne'urecha
asher atah bagadetah bah v'hi
chavertecha v'eshet britecha. Okay,
so we have these פסוקים psukim that tell us that divorcing is
really bad, or really hard. I think this is more of an
experiential claim than an evaluative judgment. I think I think all these
next claims that they're going to talk about marriage and the dissolution
of marriages, these are אגדתא agadata and they seem to be explaining
people's experiences rather than rather than being prescriptive.
אמר רבי יוחנן ואיתימא רבי אלעזר אין אשתו של אדם מתה אלא
אם כן מבקשין ממנו ממון.
Amar Rabbi Yochanan v'iteima Rabbi Elazar ein ishto shel adam meta ela
im ken mevakshin
mimeno mamon. Now this one's a weird one though. So he says
that a man's wife only dies if he owes money ואין לו
v'ein lo if he sort of just in an insane amount of
debt that's going to cause his wife to die. שנאמר אם אין
לך לשלם למה יקח משכבך מתחתיך.
Shene'emar im ein lecha l'shalem
lamah yikach mishkavcha mitachtecha.
So that the person you lie with will be taken from underneath
you. ואמר רבי יוחנן כל אדם שמתה אשתו ראשונה כאילו חרב בית
המקדש בימיו. V'amar Rabbi Yochanan kol adam shemeta ishto rishonah k'ilu charav
Beit HaMikdash b'yamav. Anybody whose first wife dies, it is as if
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash was destroyed in his days. שנאמר בן
אדם הנני לוקח ממך את מחמד עיניך במגפה לא תספוד ולא תבכה
ולא תבוא דמעתך.
Shene'emar ben adam hineni loke'ach mimcha et machmad eineicha b'magefah lo tispod
v'lo tivkeh
v'lo tavo dimatecha. וכתיב ואדבר אל העם בבקר ותמת אשתי בערב. U'chetiv
va'adaber el ha'am baboker vatamot ishti ba'erev. וכתיב הנני מחלל את מקדשי
גאון עוזכם מחמד עיניכם. U'chetiv hineni mchalel et mikdashi ge'on uzechem machmad
eineichem.
So all these פסוקים psukim from יחזקאל Yechezkel that sort of juxtapose
and compare the destruction of the temple to the death of a
first wife.
Is it just like the first wife? It's his wife dying before
him.
Oh so שמתה אשתו ראשונה shemeta ishto rishonah like she dies first.
You're totally right. If his although
sorry because later we're going to talk about the אשת נעורים eshet
ne'urim so I must have gotten confused. So his wife dies first,
that's like the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash was destroyed.
Thank you מיכל. Michal.
אמר רבי אלכסנדרי כל אדם שמתה אשתו בימיו
עולם חשך בעדו. Amar Rabbi Alexandri kol adam shemeta
ishto b'yamav olam chashach ba'ado. And for any man whose wife dies
in his days, he sort of walks around in darkness. שנאמר
אור חשך באהלו ונרו עליו ידעך. Shene'emar or chashach b'oholo v'nero alav
yidach.
רבי יוסי
בר חנינא
Rabbi
Yossi
bar Chanina רבי יוסי בר חנינא אמר Rabbi Yosi bar Chanina amar
פסיעותיו מתקצרות. pisiotov mitkatzrot. His stride becomes shorter. So sort of like
I can picture a person shuffling around more in their sadness. רש"י
Rashi also translates, sorry, whose first wife dies. ראשונה. Rishona. First wife
dies. רש"י Rashi also does say first wife. Yeah. Okay. So I
guess you could, I hear either interpretation. They both they both resonate
with the text. שנאמר, I, the only reason I would say that
it's the first wife and not in his, because first of all
only he, now we have the line of אדם שמתה אשתו בימיו,
adam shemeita ishto beyamav,
which implies that שמתה ראשונה shemeita rishona to be something else.
And the other thing I was thinking is that we just parallel
to the David story, we we're talking about his earlier wives and
then we're supposed to a
later wife. צדא? Tzarda? No, רבי אבהו אמר עצתו נופלת. Rabbi Abahu
amar itzato nofelet. His advice, his advice is not successful. So when
his wife dies he's like judgment and his ability to give counsel
becomes less
less effective. שנאמר ותשליכהו עצתו. Shene'emar vatashlicheihu itzato. אמר רבה בר בר
חנה אמר רבי יוחנן קשה לזיווגם כקריעת ים סוף.
Amar Rabbah bar Bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan kasheh
lezivugam kepriat yam suf.
Making שידוכים shidduchim is as hard as splitting the sea. שנאמר אלהים
מושיב יחידים ביתה מוציא אסירים בכושרות. Shene'emar elohim moshiv yechidim baitah motzi
asirim bakosharot. אכתי מוציא אסירים אלא כמוציא אסירים. Atzkgei motzi asirim ela
kemotzi asirim. אכתי בכושרות אלא בכי ושירות.
Atzkgei
bakosharot ela bechi veshirut.
איני, Inee, is this true that it's really so hard to make
שידוכים? shidduchim? והאמר רב יהודה אמר רב ארבעים יום קודם יצירת הולד
בת קול יוצאת ואומרת בת פלוני לפלוני. Ve'ha'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav
arbaim yom kodem yetzirat havlad bat kol yotzet ve'omeret bat ploni liploni.
What what are you talking about that it's so hard to make
שידוכים? shidduchim? We know that like forty days before a baby is
born a בת קול bat kol comes out and declares who the
person's going to be married to,
who the שידוך shidduch is going to be. I know these are
like really hard texts. I don't know, not just like the language
of the lines but they're like hard to grapple with like personally
and theologically. Talking about wife's dying and שידוכים shidduchim and
that's difficult. So I just want to name that.
שידוכים Shidduchim and today's ט"ו באב. Tu B'Av. And today's ט"ו באב.
Tu B'Av.
Yeah. So
I just know that like it's hard for me to read these
texts without thinking of things in my life and people in my
life and I imagine that is the case to some extent or
to varying extents for all of you. So thanks for just trucking
along. ואומרת בת פלוני לפלוני לא קשיא הא בזיווג ראשון הא בזיווג
שני.
Ve'omeret bat ploni liploni lo kashya ha
bezivug rishon ha bezivug sheni. Ah,
when is it easy? It's easy getting the first time you get
married. That was preordained forty days before you were born.
But for a second marriage that's that's like קריעת ים סוף. priat
yam suf. That's like really hard to do. אמר שמואל בר נחמן
לכל יש תמורה חוץ מאשת נעורים. Amar Shmuel bar Nachman lakol yesh
tmurah chutz me'eshet neurim.
For everything there's a replacement except for the wife of your youth.
שנאמר ואשת נעורים כי תמאס. Shene'emar ve'eshet neurim ki timas. So you
have this פסוק pasuk in Isaiah that even even, it's a I
think it's a rhetorical question, אשת נעורים כי תמאס, eshet neurim ki
timas, that would the the your wife of your youth ever become
despicable to you? מתני ליה רב יהודה ליצחק בריה אין אדם מוצא
קורת רוח
אלא מאשתו ראשונה. Matni lei Rav Yehuda leYitzchak breih ein adam motze
korat ruach ela me'ishto rishona. A person
only
is מוצא קורת רוח, motze korat ruach, which
means
even-keeled kind
of thing, happy.
Okay, so
a person's only going to be satisfied or have a stable
content life from his first wife. This also אשתו ראשונה ishto rishona
here now implies that it's first wife. שנאמר יהי מקורך ברוך ושמח
מאשת נעורך. Shene'emar yehi mekorecha varuch usmach me'eshet neurecha. אמר לו כגון
מן? Amar lo kegon man? So this is, so let's just be
clear this is
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says to his son רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak
that only person's the only way to get sort of satisfaction's from
your first wife. So רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak says like who? Like
what's an example of this? אמר לו כגון אמך. Amar lo kegon
imach. Like oh, like your mother. So I feel like the first
your-mom joke in the גמרא.
First time the phrase gets mentioned like oh, who is it? Like
oh, your mother. איני? Inee? Is this true? והא מקרי רב יהודה
ליצחק בריה ומוצא אני מר ממות את האשה אשר היא מצודים וחרמים.
Ve'ha mikrei Rav Yehuda leYitzchak breih umotze ani mar mibaves et
ha'isha asher hi metzudim vacharomim. So we said like
is this true that רב יהודה Rav Yehuda and his wife really
have such a great marriage? Like we have this other place where
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says to רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak that מר
אשה, mar isha, records the פסוק pasuk from קהלת, Kohelet, which would
imply that maybe his wife that that was not such a happy
marriage. אמר לו כגון מן? Amar lo kegon man? אמר לו. Amar
lo. כגון אמך *kegon imach* מצטוחא כפיפא עיבורי מעברא וממילא *mitzvavcha kefifa
iburei ma'avra ummilla*.
So yeah, it's true there are times where it gets really bad
and annoying or really bitter and terrible but then that will pass
and then it would become nice again. So the sort of talks
a little bit here about like some of the more ups and
downs of a marriage and that the idea that everything is stable
all the time is maybe
unrealistic but yeah there's times where people are angry and at discord
at times but then that also can pass. אמר רב שמואל בר
אונייא משמיה דרב אשה גולם היא ואינה כורתת ברית אלא למי שעשאה
כלי שנאמר כי בועליך עושיך ה' צבאות שמו *Amar Rav Shmuel bar
Unya mishmeih deRav ishah golem hi ve'eina
koretet brit ella lemi she'asah kli shene'emar
ki vo'alayich osayich Hashem tzeva'ot shemo*. Yeah. תניא *Tanya*. אין איש מת
אלא לאשתו ואין אשה מתה אלא לבעלה אין איש מת אלא לאשתו
שנאמר וימת אלימלך איש נעמי ואין אשה מתה אלא לבעלה שנאמר ואני
בבואי מפדן מתה עלי רחל *Ein ish met ella le'ishto ve'ein ishah
metah ella leva'alah ein ish met ella le'ishto shene'emar vayamot Elimelech ish
Na'omi ve'ein ishah metah ella leva'alah shene'emar va'ani vevo'i miPadan metah alai
Rachel*. I was thinking about how when one person dies when a
person one either a man or woman dies the person who's sort
of affected by it the most or who feels experiences their death
the most is their partner or spouse. אין רואים אותו *Ein ro'in
oto*. תנו רבנן מלך מסתפר בכל יום כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. מערב
שבת לערב שבת כהן Kohen הדיוט אחת לשלושים יום מלך מסתפר בכל
יום שנאמר מלך ביופיו תחזינה עיניך *Tanu Rabbanan melech mistaper bechol yom
kohen gadol me'erev Shabbat le'erev Shabbat kohen hedyot achat lishloshim yom melech
mistaper bechol yom shene'emar melech beyofyo techazenah eineycha*. So here we're given
the haircut schedule for three different groups. You have the king gets
a haircut every day. He's always has to look impeccable, impeccably perfect.
The Kohen Gadol gets it once a week because each week the
new each week a new group comes into the Mikdash every Friday
a new
group
of Kohanim comes to serve and he needs to look good on
that first day when they all show up and a Kohen Hedyot
needs to get a haircut once every thirty days. כהן גדול מערב
שבת *Kohen Gadol me'erev Shabbat*. אמר רב שמואל בר נחמן אמר רב
יוחנן הואיל ומשמרות כהונה *Amar Rav Shmuel bar Nachman amar Rav Yochanan
ho'il umishmarot kehunah* sorry. So the reason why the Kohen Gadol is
once every erev Shabbat is exactly what we said that since there's
a new mishmar then he's got to look spiffy for them. כהן
הדיוט אחת לשלושים יום דכתיב וראשם לא יגלחו ופרע לא ישלחו כסום
יכסמו את ראשיהם *Kohen Hedyot achat lishloshim yom dechtiv verosham lo yegalchu
uphera lo yeshalchu kasom yichsemu et rosheihem*. וילפינן פרע פרע מנזיר דכתיב
הכא ופרע לא ישלחו וכתיב התם גדל פרע שער ראשו מה להלן
שלושים אף כאן שלושים *Veyalpinan phera phera miNazir dechtiv hacha uphera lo
yeshalchu vechtiv hatam gadel phera se'ar rosho mah lehallan shloshim af kan
shloshim*. So we know that the hair cutting situation of the Kohen
Gadol of the Kohanim is regulated based on this Rambam's the first
to say this so I'm not a hundred percent sure but based
on
early
other Ancient Near East practices in terms of how the priests would
dress and what kind of haircuts they would have so it was
highly regulated in the Torah so but
and we know this thirty days just because we have parallel sources
with in the case of Nazir where we know that the Nazir
that the neder lasts at least thirty days. אמר רב מתנה דאמר
קרא *Amar Rav Matnah de'amar kra* sorry. ותנן נמי סתם נזירות שלושים
יום *Vetenan nami stam nezirut shloshim yom*. Stam nezirut is thirty days.
ואסמכתא מנלן *Ve'asmachta manalan*?
So how does he know this? אמר רב מתנה דאמר קרא קדוש
יהיה בגימטריא תלתין *Amar Rav Matnah de'amar kra kadosh yihyeh be'gematriya taltin*.
קדוש יהיה *Kadosh yihyeh*. So it says he will be holy and
יהיה *yihyeh* is yud hey yud hey is ten five ten five
that's gematriya of thirty and that's how we know stam nezirut is
thirty days. אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי אימא לא לירבו כלל *Amar
leh Rav Pappa le'Abaye eima lo lirbu klal*. אימא לא
לירבו כלל *Eima lo lirbu klal*.
Maybe we should get the haircut Kohanim should get the haircut more
than every thirty days.
The point being don't learn this from Nazir.
The point being why if they're not allowed to have messy hair
why wait thirty days?
Yeah why wait at all? Okay let's go with that. אמר ליה
אי כתיב ופרע לא ישלחו כדקאמרת השתא דכתיב פרע פרע לירבויי לא
ישלחו *Amar leh i ktiv uphera lo yeshalchu kedeka'amart hashta dechtiv phera
phera leribuyei lo yeshalchu*.
They
should not grow their hair at all but shave their heads instead.
Oh maybe right oh לא לירבו *lo lirbu* they shouldn't grow their
hair at all. And no that's the whole idea of not growing
a phera implies that there should be like some sort of haircut
that occurs.
That's a strange suggestion. Rav Pappa knows the pasuk.
That's weird. Okay.
אי הכי האידנא נמי *I hachi ha'idna nami*.
If so today also how come the how come the כהן doesn't
get a haircut? How come regular כהנים Kohanim don't get haircuts once
every thirty days? דומיא דיין מה יין בזמן ביאה Dumya d'yayin mah
yayin bizman biah who is אסור assur שלא בזמן ביאה שרי. shelo
bizman biah shari.
No, it's similar to wine. Just like wine, when they're going—this is
ביאת המקדש biat haMikdash not ביאה biah with a—ביאה biah with a
woman—so just like wine then at the time they're going into the
מקדש, Mikdash, then it's אסור assur for them to drink. שלא בזמן
ביאה, Shelo bizman biah, but if it's not their time to go
into the מקדש, Mikdash, then it's permitted to drink. אף פרוע ראש
בזמן ביאה אסור, שלא בזמן ביאה שרי. Af prua rosh bizman biah
assur, shelo bizman biah shari. So also in terms of the haircutting
situation, at the time when they're going into the מקדש, Mikdash, it's
אסור. assur. The time they're not, it's all permitted.
ויין שלא בזמן ביאה שרי? V'yayin shelo bizman biah shari? And is
it true that the כהנים Kohanim are allowed to drink when they're
not on their משמר, mishmar, when they're not entering into temple to
do the service? דתניא, we have
a
ברייתא. רבי אומר, אני כהנים אסורין לשתות—oh, Rabbi omer, ani Kohanim assurim
lishtot sorry—רבי יהודה אומר, אומר אני כהנים אסורין לשתות יין לעולם. Rabbi
Yehuda omer, omer ani Kohanim assurim lishtot yayin l'olam. Rabbi Yehuda
says, "I say כהנים Kohanim are never allowed to drink wine." אבל
מה אעשה שתקנתו קלקלתו. Aval mah e'eseh shetakanto kalkalato. Because I really
think כהנים Kohanim should never drink, but what can I do? תקנתו
קלקלתו. Takanto kalkalato. This is like a great, great idea that
כהנים Kohanim currently do drink.
So if the temple gets restored, then they're not going to be
able to drink anymore. So you start with a situation where something
that they, like, are supposedly praying for and yearning for would actually
be like not good for them because then they'd no longer be
allowed to drink wine, we presume. This is what we, I guess,
we'd consider like where the incentives are all backwards, where the כהנים
Kohanim really enjoy drinking wine, and if the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
were to get rebuilt, then they wouldn't be able to drink wine.
It's fine, I guess. I don't know, it's just something. ואמר
אביי, כמאן שתו כהני חמרא האידנא? כרבי.
V'amar Abaye, k'man shatu
Kahane chamra haidna? K'Rabbi. So who holds this? שתו כהני חמרא
האידנא כרבי. Shatu Kahane chamra haidna k'Rabbi. מכלל דרבנן אסרי. Miklal d'rabanan
asre. התם היינו טעמא מהרה יבנה בית המקדש. Hatam hainu ta'ama meheira
yibaneh Beis HaMikdash. So what's the reason why—so the fact—sorry—the fact that
one—that רבי permits it—permits the
drinking—implies that there's somebody who says it's אסור, assur, and that was
the דרבנן. d'rabanan. So התם היינו טעמא, hatam hainu ta'ama, the reason
is מהרה יבנה בית המקדש ובעינן כהן הראוי לעבודה.
meheira yibaneh Beis
HaMikdash u'vainan Kohen haraoy l'avoda. So here, this is a great line,
so it's a דרשה drasha on the word מהרה. meheira. It's not
like מהרה יבנה בית המקדש meheira yibaneh Beis HaMikdash that like, "Ah,
it should come speedily in our days," like it should come soon.
Point is מהרה, meheira, it's going to happen really fast. Like at
some point, boom, temple is going to be there. We're going to
need to make sure there's a sober כהן who can—who can serve
in the temple. And if they're permitted to drink, then they'd—by then—all
be drunk. And that would—that would be a problem. So the גמרא
says ובעינן כהן הראוי לעבודה וליכא. u'vainan Kohen haraoy l'avoda v'leika.
We're not going to have one. הכא נמי בעינא כהן הראוי לעבודה
וליכא. Hacha nami b'ina Kohen haraoy l'avoda v'leika. So too, the כהנים
Kohanim should get a haircut every thirty days in order to ensure
that he'll also have the appropriate hair—haircut for—in order to serve in
the temple. הכא אפשר דמסתפר ועייל. Hacha efshar d'mistaper v'ayel. So we
say, "He'll just get a haircut and go in." התם נמי אפשר
דניים פורתא ועייל. Hatam nami efshar d'nayam purta v'ayel.
Just wait a minute and go—go up.
You're saying wait
to sober up.
Yeah, just to wait. Yeah.
דאמר רב אחא, דרך מיל ושינה כל שהוא מפיגין את היין.
D'amar Rav Acha, derech mil v'shaina kol shehu mefigin
et hayayin.
If you just walk a—take a walk—take a walk and go to
sleep—we all know—that's going to abate the—the drunkenness. But either/or.
Walk a mile or take a nap. נים, Nayam, taking a nap,
then they're sober again. Okay. ולאו איתמר עלה אמר רב נחמן
אמר רבה
בר אבוה לא שנו אלא ששתה כדי רביעית אבל יותר מכדי רביעית
כל שכן שדרך טורח ושינה משכרתו.
V'lav
itmar ala amar
Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar Avuha lo shanu ela sheshata k'dei revi'it
aval yoter mik'dei revi'it kol sheken she'derech torach u'shaina meshachrato.
That's walking a mile or taking a nap, that's only true if
you drank a little bit. But if you drank a lot, then
you're going to need to do a lot more.
רב אשי אמר שתויי יין דמחלי עבודה
גזרו
בהו. Rav Ashi amar shutyei yayin d'machli avoda gazru
behu.
So they drank
wine because of the מחלי עבודה...
machle avoda... Oh, מחול *mechol*, right. So the reason why I can't
drink wine is cause you're gonna actually profane the profane the Temple,
you're gonna right, you're gonna pass the להבדיל בין הקודש ובין החול
*Lehavdil bein hakodesh uvein hachol*.
Cool. פרוע ראש ולא חל עבודה לא קעסר ביה רבנן *Parua rosh
velo chal avodah lo ka'sar bei rabbanan*. So yeah, that's true for
wine, 'cause wine is gonna be is gonna profane something. But not
having a haircut is not a big deal. So maybe, but we
have in a ברייתא *Braisa* דאילו שבמיתה פרוע ראש ושתוי יין *De'ilu
shebemita parua rosh u'shtui yayin*, בשלמא שתוי יין דכתיב יין ושכר אל
תשת אתה ובניך אתך ולא תמותו *bishlama shtui yayin dechtiv yayin veshichar
al tesht atah uvanecha itach velo tamutu*, אלא פרוע ראש מנלן *ela
parua rosh menalan*, דאיתקש שתוי יין לפרוע ראש *de'itkesh shtui yayin leparua
rosh*, ראשם לא יפרעו ופרע לא ישלחו *rosham lo yifrau vaperah lo
yeshalechu*, ויין לא ישתו *veyayin lo yishtu*, גמר מה שתוי
יין במיתה
אף פרוע ראש במיתה *gemar
ma shtui yayin bemitah af parua rosh bemitah*. So the point is
if you go if you serve drunk, you're gonna there's gonna be
death. These are פסוקים *pesukim* from יחזקאל *Yechezkel*. Yes. So if you
drink if you drink wine, you're gonna die. And then also if
you go in without having the proper haircutting situation, that's also gonna
result in death. מינה מה שתוי יין דמחלי עבודה אף פרוע ראש
דמחלי עבודה *minah ma shtui yayin demachlei avodah af parua rosh demachlei
avodah*. And that implies also that both of these are gonna profane
the עבודה *avodah*. So קשיא *kashya* seems to be מחלוקת *machloket*. So
אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי *amar leih Ravina leRav Ashi* האי עד
דלא אתא יחזקאל מאן אמרה *hai ad delo ata Yechezkel man amrah*?
So until יחזקאל *Yechezkel* came, how did we how do we know
this? So I think we
had the פסוקים *pesukim* of ראשם לא יפרעו ופרע לא ישלחו *rosham
lo yifrau vaperah lo yeshalechu*.
These פסוקים *pesukim* about having the proper haircut, those are פסוקים *pesukim*
from יחזקאל *Yechezkel*. So he's like, I don't understand, like this is
like a classic, so they're asking this question which is anytime anytime
you have like a really late הלכה *halacha* in תנ"ך *Tanakh*, did
they what did they do before יחזקאל *Yechezkel* had these פסוקים *pesukim*?
הא דאמר רב חסדא דבר זה מתורת משה רבינו לא למדנו עד
שבא יחזקאל ולימדנו *ha de'amar Rav Chisda davar zeh mi'torat Moshe Rabbeinu
lo lamdanu ad sheba Yechezkel velimdanu*. So there was a מסורה *mesorah*
from משה רבינו *Moshe Rabbeinu* but it wasn't ever actually explicitly taught
until יחזקאל *Yechezkel* came in תנ"ך *Tanakh*. כל בן נכר ערל לב
וערל בשר לא יבא אל מקדשי לשרתני *kol ben nechar arel lev
ve'arel basar lo yavo el mikdashi lesharetani*. עד דלא אתא יחזקאל מאן
אמרה *ad delo ata Yechezkel man amrah*? אלא גמרא גמירי לה ואתא
יחזקאל ואסמכה אקרא *ela gemara gemiri lah ve'ata Yechezkel ve'asmachah akra*. Or
so either one way there's a מסורה *mesorah* and then it got
taught later. Another is that there was a מסורה *mesorah* about the
הלכה *halacha* and then later at some point they needed to pin
it on a פסוק *pasuk*. And then they had the פסוק *pasuk*
to pin it on. הכי נמי גמרא גמירי לה ואתא יחזקאל ואסמכה
אקרא *hachi nami gemara gemiri lah ve'ata Yechezkel ve'asmachah akra*. So so
too that's exactly what happened here as well. מאי ראשם לא יפרעו
ופרע לא ישלחו *mai rosham lo yifrau vaperah lo yeshalechu*? תנא כמין
תספורת לולינית *tana kemin tisporet lulianit*. So what kind of haircut was
it? So it was this לולינית *lulianit* haircut. I guess it was
whatever the style, the style was. מאי תספורת לולינית *mai tisporet lulianit*?
אמר רב חסדא אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל תספורת יחידה *amar Rav
Chisda amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel tisporet yechida*.
It was a unique, it was a unique haircut. היכי דמי *heichi
dami*? אמר רב אשי ראשו של זה בצד עיקרו של זה *amar
Rav Ashi rosho shel zeh betzad ikaro shel zeh*. So I don't
I don't is there a picture of what this haircut is? It
sounds like I mean maybe someone has a different idea.
A Soncino's rather vague description of the haircut of the High Priest.
It sounds like the head of the end of one hair connected
to the root of a different hair.
According to the רמב"ם *Rambam*, whose words are entirely clear, the High
Priest's hair was cut uniformly short so that one hair would not
fold over another and so that it would
appear heavily cropped like
a field that
was harvested all at once.
That seems like not a unique haircut. Yes. Rows of pearls.
Yes, it felt like the description felt more curly to me that
the ראש *rosh* of one was bent over to touch the root
of the next hair. לולין
*Lulian*?
לולין *Lulian* is like a somebody in the circus. At least in
modern Hebrew. I will look what the right word is, but it's
like a whatever.
Like a whimsical, like a...
A clown? No, it's not a clown. He works like a trapeze?
A trapeze artist? Huh.
So that's why, right here. Yeah, of course.
Trapeze hair, yes.
It's the trapeze hair, yeah. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל *amar Rav
Yehuda amar Shmuel*.
Sorry.
שאלו את רבי איזהו
תספורת של
כהן גדול *sha'alu et Rabbi eizehu tisporet shel Kohen Gadol*?
So it says, so they asked רבי *Rabbi* like what is the
כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol*, what was his haircut like? An acrobat. אמר
להן *amar lahen* צאו וראו מתספורת של בן אלעשה Ben Alasha *tze'u
ur'u mitisporet shel Ben Elasah*. So they go out. out and see
the haircut of בן אלעשה.
So תניא רבי אומר לא על חינם פיזר בן אלעשה ממון רב
אלא כדי להראות בו תספורת של כהן גדול. Tanya Rebbe omer lo
al chinam pizer Ben Alasha mamon rav ela kedei lehar'ot bo tisporet
shel Kohen Gadol. So he
said בן אלעשה was not just wasting his money on fancy haircuts.
He was spending his money in order to sport the haircut of
the כהן גדול.
Okay,
so
this is written
in...
so
there like there's got to be some error in the middle that
we... because
you don't know what it refers to. So we're thinking of the
Temple is so imminent that they are still worried about
haircuts.